O.  Welcome back to Lam Rim.
Today we will review the entire lesson.
That's good for me.  I want to do my own review.
The format of doing separate episodes
and then doing them at different times,
you kind of lose the thread of the whole teaching.
I thought it would be good today if we went back
to the beginning and reviewed the
overall flow of the lam rim that we have been studying.
I will do this flow based on IDIM, with idea pictures,
which we use to teach ACI teachers.
ACI teachers
are expected to look at one of these images
and identify the idea behind it.
I think, Tim, we said how many there would be?   A thousand or more?
How many?
500, something like that.  So it's like taking a test,
to test someone just based on pictures.
So we're going to throw this image at you.
So I challenge you during this review
when we put up a picture,
I'll give you a few seconds and see if you
can remember what the picture was about?
Okay, and this is a good review
of all the lessons we've done.  Alright, here it is...
Mr. Sejii's first photo.
This image should remind you
that we are in the midst of a practice
for people of moderate capacity
and what they are trying to achieve is nirvana.
They try to get out of the wheel of life, from all the suffering for themselves personally.  This is
where the Buddha taught three trainings
that will help you achieve your personal nirvana.  The
third practice is understanding emptiness, understanding the pen.  The
second training is meditation.
On a deep level, both of these can only be done in a quiet place,
at a specific time of day, when you are completely focused on the meditation cushion.
At a deeper level, both should be done
at specific periods of the day.
But the first, the basis of the second is to be kind to others.
You could call it morality.
You can call it an ethical way of life,
but ultimately it is about doing good to others.
That is the foundation,
which is always available to us throughout the day.
This is one of the three great trainings of Buddhism,
aimed at helping us attain nirvana.
And it is available to us all day long.
So in this picture,
you can see Seiji helping Geshe Michael use his computer.
Which is one of the best things a young person can do for an old person.
Next image;  see if you remember what this picture is?
What's your guess?
This woman does her taxes.  What made him enter the lam rim system?
that makes him...
a dharma teacher.  When I say dharma teacher, or tantra teacher,
I know the image that comes to your mind.
Some big 'lamas' are on thrones and they have big yellow hats.
Maybe they ring bells and a little drum and they.....
And you think;  'Oh, that's a dharma teacher.  That is a real dharma teacher'.
Or you think of the old image of Nagarjuna,
and he is very mystical.
In lam rim, what we learn
is this woman.
He has several children, he is married
and he is a dharma teacher.  He is a real dharma teacher.
Pabongka Rinpoche said, don't think that a dharma teacher has to sit on a throne
reciting Tantric rituals.
What is this woman doing?
He pays taxes.
Honestly paying your taxes is really hard in my country.
It may take a few weeks to do your taxes and
to really do them carefully,
to really do them honestly,
to pay every penny that you owe.
This makes him...
He has an incredible first training as a good person;
be kind to others.
That makes him a real dharma teacher.
Forget the 'old' pictures with the big hat you had,
and the ringing bell.  Okay, that's easy.
Anyone can do that.
To be kind to others is difficult
and to maintain your morality, to maintain your ethics is
also difficult.
Next,
I will give you some time.  Do you remember what this is about?
The quote in lam rim is tsul trim den pay ge long ud dang den (TSUL KHRIMS LDAN PA'I DGE SLONG 'OD DANG LDAN)
Someone who truly keeps their vows,
truly keeps their Buddhist guidelines, especially the 10 guidelines,
they shine, truly shine.
A person who makes a healthy, humble effort to keep their commitments,
to maintain the ten good karma and
be kind to others,
they have a kind of peaceful look on their face,
they glow.
When they walk into a room, you know it.
Everyone started to feel better, like Tim and Seiji.
It is the light of the world.
Buddha said, those people are the light of the world.
There are Christian expressions;
Don't put candles in a basket, let the world see your happy face.
And it is a true guiding light for the whole world.
Next image IDIM #4
This is the cliff I visited with my partner Veronica on her birthday, during this lam rim.
They talk about sunset, for which the Tibetan word is nub pa (NUB PA).
It also means west because the sun sets in the west;
nub pa means
sunset and it is a very sad verb.
This is a very sad idea in dharma, The
most famous place at the end of Abhidharmakosha;  Treasure House of Higher Wisdom.  The
Treasure House of Higher Knowledge by Master Vasabhandu, and he says;
"the sun of dharma, the light of dharma, will set in this world."
We will lose the light of dharma in this world.  This world will plunge into darkness.
After some time,
Buddhism will disappear in this world.
At first they disappeared from people's minds, but they still exist in libraries.
The books are still in the library.  Maybe a library that John Brady hasn't discovered yet.
And then, they'll disappear from the library too and then they'll be gone forever.
I put the picture here because Pabongka Rinpoche made a special point, he said:
'if you cannot keep your commitments, if you cannot be kind to others,
then we can say the dharma has left this world.'
The light of dharma has left the world within you.
The sun has set within your own chest,
which would be a very sad thing if we did not keep our promise.
Next image.
We call this retreat Love in the Time of Virus.
The bottom line is that during a very difficult time in the world,
if you keep your commitments,
if you are kind to others,
when things are scary, and the virus is spreading.
We don't know where, we don't know how, and
we don't know how many people will die.
If during difficult times you do something kind for others,
this is much, much more powerful.
He mentioned, if you remember, a 5-star Buddhist paradise,
which is like the perfect place.
It's easy to be a good person, everyone there is a good person.
That's not a big achievement.                                            It's not a big deal,
and the seeds aren't strong enough
to be nice in a group of nice people.
To be kind when people attack you, when people are afraid,
when people are not kind to each other and to be someone
who stands up and shares things in difficult times -
then that is a very pure person.
That's great karma.  That's incredible karma, much more powerful.
I think this virus is a very good time, and
it is a very good opportunity for all of us to show
- are we really Buddhist?   Are we truly practicing the bodhisattva path?
Can we help others even when things are very difficult.
Next image.
This one is hard to remember, I have a hard time remembering it.
I'll give you some time to try to figure out what this picture is about.
Pabongka Rinpoche quoted several books
with very, very common endings in different books.
He quoted a famous person, namely Lobsang Gyelway Tenpa (BLO BZANG RGYAL BA'I BSTAN PA) ... cik (CIG)
may the teachings of the winner ...
Lobsang Drakpa, Je Tsongkapa
spread in this world.
You think, we should go online.
We have to translate this lamrim into various languages.
We must spread the good news to as many people as we can.
That is the end of the prayer and it should be after this lamrim or video
and we should share the dharma with others.
We should spread dharma in the world.
In this part of the lamrin, Pabongka Rinpoche says;
the place you should spread the dharma is here, in your own heart.
Don't think that spreading dharma means, trying to translate videos
into more languages ​​or something like that.  It is a very important way to spread the dharma.
But he said, if you spread it in your own heart,
of course it will spread outside of you because this world comes from your heart,
actually from your heart chakra actually.
Next picture #7
Try to remember what this picture is about?  I'll give it a moment.
This is my favorite topic;
have a personal relationship with another person, like these two people.
In my opinion and in tantra, it is one of the happiest things that can happen to you.
It's one of the greatest things that can happen to you.
Anyone will tell you the reason the whole world is looking for a partner,
is to make people happy.
It is one of the greatest joys when things go well.
It's one of the greatest joys you can have but
you know and I know when it doesn't go well,
it's one of the greatest pains in life.
Why is it relevant to this lesson?
If your morality is good,
this is the happiest thing in your life.
And if you violate your morality, it is also the same thing that will make you miserable.
It's like having a good woman or man, who is your partner, the
same person who makes you really happy,
can also make you really miserable.
So in this case, the vinaya, your personal practice of goodness,
good behavior, compared to a partner
who can make you the best thing in life
or the worst thing in your life - the same person.
IDIM next #8
This one is tricky.  See if you remember?
I'll take a sip of my green drink.
Thank you Vimala.
This actually symbolizes breaking your commitment.  Pulling weeds
represents breaking your commitments.
Why would destroying this plant violate your commitment?
If you are a gardener you know that you have to pull the weeds out
before the seeds are ready to burst.
If you wait until the seedlings are ready to emerge and then
start pulling the plants out,
you will end up spreading about a thousand seedlings.
For the next month or next year you will have thousands of weeds growing back.
So you have to attack the weeds early.
This refers to a very radical statement
that Buddha said
ge long dak sok dang drel shing shi wa ni lay (DGE SLONG DAG SROG DANG BRAL ZHING SHI BA NI BLA'I) It is
better to die
than to break your vows.  Why?
When you break a vow,
you sow a seed
that will continue to grow for many lifetimes.
If you die you destroy one mind body complex.
If you die, you destroy a very useful temple,
a temple of the physical and the mind.  You lost one.
But if you break the commitment,
you lose a lot of mind-body complexes.
You damage your body and mind for many lifetimes.
And you create a moving seed
that will destroy many lives.
Buddha said, it is better to die than to break a vow and
that is not a metaphor.  He was being very literal
when he said that.  Better to die than break your commitment.
There is a joke in the lamrim.
We vow never to give up bodhichitta even at the cost of our lives.
There is a famous saying, all our life we ​​are waiting
to be put in jail
by some bad people.
They came with knives and they said 'give up your bodhisattva vows or die today'.
Then we will say;
'I choose to die'.
And they kill us.
I think we've all been waiting for this moment since we took that oath.
We're all waiting for these guys to show up with knives and threaten us.
But actually we are the ones with the knives.  We threaten our own bodhisattva vows every day.
We must make this decision every day when we decide to keep our vows carefully.
It's hard to find the people who put you in jail, and say;
I will kill you if you don't hand over your bodhisattva vows.
Next image.
See if you remember.  I'll give you some time to try to remember it.
This is a reference....
we have a Mixed Nuts translation team
and we are translating the old vinaya texts;
monastic vows, nun's vows.
They talk about vows, traditions that we are not supposed to...
...when you become a monk or a nun they give you robes,
they give you a small buddha statue,
and they give you a sieve.
And in ancient India you were supposed to carry this sieve with you.
When you drink from the river,
you should filter the water first to make sure you don't kill any small insects.
We mentioned a well-known tradition in the vinaya:
if two monks go to the river to drink water
to get some water,
then they must choose the best monk to check the water.
Don't choose someone who doesn't care about insects.  Try to find a guy who loves bugs
and have them check the water because they will be more careful.
What is the point?
We're talking about a kind of ecological vow,
where monks and nuns aren't even supposed to pick green leaves
from plants because they're the homes of tiny creatures.
This means, honoring even the smallest vows,
keeping them very seriously because the results are multiplied.
Then, it is important to maintain your morality at a very subtle level,
at a very subtle level.
If I were to write a bodhisattva vow,
I would write an extra bodhisattva vow about
not offending your bodhisattva vow.
There's nothing more annoying than
someone telling you that they kept their oath and
that's why they have to be an asshole today.
Keep your vows sweet.  Keep them happy.  Do not exaggerate.
Don't bother others with your swearing because your swearing doesn't bother others.
Keeping small vows, keeping them quietly.  Keep them private, don't advertise.
There is a saying in Islam... the left hand should not let the right hand know what it is doing.
That means, don't advertise your vows.  Just keep them quiet.
Keeping them at a very subtle level.
Next image.
This is the idea that being kind to others
is like planting a tree.
Today I went to Cafe PeachTree.
to check on something and
Stanley and Alison and I planted a peach tree there,
when we first started the PeachTree Cafe Morning Show
And I wanted to tell you guys that three peaches came out this week
and we have peaches now.
What that means is, keep your basic practices.
Take care of the roots, and plants of good karma
by keeping your vows, by being kind to others.
Then it will grow into a tree.
And the peach tree we planted
five months ago or something,
is already bearing a lot of fruit.
If you don't take care of it when it's small, you'll have nothing.
If you take care of your basic Buddhist practice,
which is being kind to others,
then the fruits will be thousands and thousands and thousands.
It will come, it will grow
big... it will grow into a tree
that will give peaches every year and for many years you will have peaches.
Take care...protect....
This child protects the bud carefully.
Protect your morality.
Next image.
If I remember correctly, there are four conditions
that can cause you to break your commitment.
If you take the bodhisattva commitment
or you take the vinaya pratimoksha commitment,
or even if you take the diamond path tantric commitment.
I think there are four.  Pabongka Rinpoche reviewed... maybe more than that....
basically, there are certain conditions
that will help you break your vows.
If you want to break your vow, there are some specific ways to do it.
The first;
that is, if you don't know what your vows are,
that's a great way to break them.  If you want to break them,
then don't study them and,
one of the annoying things, I have a lot of annoying things about the dharma,
is teachers who give big initiations,
and they don't explain to the people who are taking the initiation
that they have just taken vows.
There are hundreds of vows you take when you get initiated,
and you will break them if you don't know them.
It is the teacher's responsibility
to train you in your vows before you receive the initiation ceremony.
If they don't offer to train you, I wouldn't take initiation from them.  The
best way to break your vows, the first way, is to not know them.
Read the recipe before you start cooking.
That's what Veronica says every time I cook.
Next image.
It was a woman who said, 'Yeah, it's no big deal'.
A vow not to cut greenery without a prayer,
come on, that's a bit extreme.  That's a bit too much, not so important.
Only a few insects
may use the leaves occasionally as a roof.
It's not a big deal.  The
second best way to break your vow
is to have this attitude;
'Oh that one isn't that important, I'm looking after the big one.'
Next.
If we get klesha, meaning if we have some negativity
in our mind, it is a great way to break your vows.
Feeling annoyed with other people or
obsessed with getting something or money or
addicted to Netflix at night.
.... by the way, it's not wrong to watch Netflix, but I'm talking about
hurting other people because you want to go home and watch Netflix.  That's a problem.
This is called a gang fight.
What's the story?
Attacking the biggest person on the other side.
Find out who the leader of the other side is,
and don't talk, don't negotiate, don't shout at each other,
walk up to him and hit him on the head.
And then the whole other side will collapse.
Identify your worst habits,
and attack them first.  It's a way to keep your vows.
Next.
.... by the way at my age,
I'm not saying how old I am,
but all this young love is
so ridiculous from my age perspective.
I can say that with experience because I have it.
But this thing about,
oh, she's the most beautiful woman in the world.
He is the most handsome man in the world.
First of all, my oldest brother,
he said the funniest thing.  He said, do you like that girl?  I said, yes.
He said, you want to spend your life with him?  I said, yes.
He said, check on his mother first.
See what her mother looks like?  I said, Mom looks terrible.  He was overweight, he looked tired and he looked terrible.
And he said, well, what do you think he used to look like,
So think about this?
If you are attached to someone's appearance,
or something physical, or something less important about someone.
It will change and you will see them get sick,
you will see them get old.  You will see them having diarrhea and vomiting.
If you are unlucky you will see them inside and in operation sometime.
Don't fool yourself
that it's worth hurting others
to get the most beautiful woman or man.  This is not worth it.
This won't last long.  It's nice to have a relationship but have it for the right reasons.
Next.
If you have problems with anger
or you get angry easily.
Try fantasizing about giving this person
something they would love to have.  This is called maitri,
jampa,
love.
Fantasizing, trying to remember how good it would be to give someone...
something they love, something they want.
Try to have this attitude.
If you don't feel friendly towards others
then do some fantasy, which means meditating
on giving them something they would really like.
Next.
I'll give you some time on this one.  I bet you don't remember what this one is?
The team cheated by looking ahead.
What is this one?
This is about pride.
Pride will also be an obstacle to keeping your vows.
And... one of the most common types of pride
in the monastic context, where this book is commonly taught;
is how much you know about ancient scriptures, how many facts you have collected
in life.
This is something I really enjoy, about the understanding of dharma
and the more you collect
the more special you feel.
Pabongka Rinpoche said, 'All the dharma you've ever studied in your life, all the things you've memorized,
all the things you've debated,
all the geshe titles you've ever had,
compared to what's left to know, you know nothing.
You are like a worm at the bottom of the sea,
and sometimes you come out and look at the stars.
Many stars have planets around them.
There are people on those planets.  There are things to know about those people.
There are things we know,
that we are so proud of,
that are a small fraction of what you can know.
So don't be arrogant.
Next.
One of the big motivations for breaking your vows
or your commitments is morality, which will stop you from attaining nirvana, which will stop you from attaining both
levels of the lamrim - personal nirvana;
is to understand emptiness, to study emptiness.
If you realize, that the evil things
that other people do to you,
come directly from what you did last week.
Then you won't make a big mistake.  The more you can learn about emptiness,
the more you can learn about cause and effect, the initial dependence
that means this person comes from my seed,
then it will be easier to keep your vows.  It's getting easier to maintain.  So study, study, study.
I had a teacher, an old Mongolian teacher, who was very old with tuberculosis and
he used to say,
'He is very good.  You're so proud, you have a huge amount of pride from Princeton and
then the geshe,
it really, really helps...
You'll push yourself harder
just to look smart.
That's lucky, but later try to give up.
Just learn to be a good person.  This is so funny
He gave me Adam's text on his deathbed.
I remember this.
Next.
This is technically the fourth cause.  No.
One of the reasons for breaking your vows or losing your commitment.  It is
very difficult in the modern world
to keep your mind on the promise when you are very busy.  When things move very fast.
There are a thousand things to see on the internet,
and life moves so fast.  It
's hard to maintain self-awareness;
did I break an oath, did I do something to hurt someone?
You have to slow down, go back to your vows
and have some kind of sensitive awareness
of the fact that you have a commitment not to hurt others.
The busier you are, the more careful you have to be.
It's easy to get annoyed with your colleagues when you're busy.
They're trying to tell you something and
you've got 10 things going on at work and you're...
'I don't have time to listen right now.
My boss gave me 10 things to do.'
That's when you have to slow down
and go back to your vows.
Don't forget your commitment to be kind to others even when you are
very stressed, very busy.  It is
better to break some business commitments than to be
nervous and stressed and unkind to people,
it is better not to pay a bill or miss a business meeting or
not do as well as you can at work,
if it means keeping your mind clear.
Next image.
This is a woman who buys useless things in a shop.
See if you remember this story.
He said, 'Oh this box is so beautiful.  He went to the mall.  He bought this .....
.... what is a home improvement store,
where you buy things?  Crate and Barrel.
He went to Crate and Barrel in America.  She said, 'Oh my husband will love this box.'
He didn't know what he would use it for
but he would take it home.
Then when she came home, her husband would say, 'You're crazy, this is a worthless little box.
We have a lot of trash at home.  Return.  Get your money back.
Should he go to the gas station and try to return it?
No, that's not where he bought the box.  This is a bit obvious but we have to say it.
If you buy a stupid box,
because you like it and you think your husband will like it, which turns out he doesn't...
And he asks you to return the box.
Don't take it back to a different place.  Take it back to where you bought it.
What does it mean?
You have to pay me.
When you are in confession,
if you break a vow,
try to go back to the person who gave you the vow.
Try to confess in front of the person who gave you the oath.
Can you confess in your own home?
Not for the oaths you take from others, in general.
If you don't take vows
from others, then it might be okay at home
to confess in front of a Buddha statue or something like that, in extreme cases it's okay.
But in general,
if you can go back to the person who gave you your vows,
confess your sins to them openly - don't be shy.  We are not shy all day long.
Therefore, do not be shy about your oath, and say 'why is that'
go directly to your teacher and say I broke this stupid oath.
And your teacher is 'wow, you're such a bad person.'  You're like, yeah, yeah.
Get over it, then you feel clean, you feel good.
You can be shy about many things in life, but don't be shy about your vows.
If you break an oath, go tell someone
and that's how you get rid of it.  You get rid of the problem.
If you hold onto it and hide it, and if you spend more time hiding it than admitting it
or keeping it, then that's stupid
and you won't feel good.  You won't feel clean.
Be open with your teacher.  I have this problem.  I have a bad habit.
Karma will be destroyed, seeds will be destroyed.
Your teacher will say, "I heard that before, you told me."  But you have to be persistent and keep telling them.  The
next picture
is about .....wait, do you remember?
Again, it's about respecting the
small details of the vows.
This is actually a vow for monks, they have to brush their teeth,
with a stick called so shing (SO SHING)
it is a stick that you are supposed to use to clean your teeth,
you just cut it from a tree and use it.
This is a toothbrush.
He said, monks should have toothbrushes and you should brush your teeth.
This may seem like a small thing;
"Wait, I'm trying to keep my tantric vow to go to Amitabha's heaven"
and protect all sentient beings and Buddha said, 'Yes, but in the meantime,
could you brush your teeth every day.
You think, but that's not really a big vow.
But it's the little things that make a buddhist paradise.
These are the little things that Bodhisattvas do,
which is being kind to others.
Of course, everyone in the world would...
...stop a nuclear war or something if they could.  I mean, that's obvious.
But are you a good enough person,
that you don't even want people to smell your breath?
If it might hurt them?
If you are very sensitive
about small things that might hurt others,
then we can say you are guarding your morals.
And then it's the little details that put the finishing touches
on your buddha paradise, which you see in the next picture.
This guy decorated a Christmas tree...
If you've ever done a Christmas tree, but those of us who were raised in the Christian tradition,
our parents made us make a Christmas tree.
There's something cool about
putting the last ornament on.
Everyone looked at the tree and they said, 'Is it finished' and they said, 'Yes, it's finished'.
He said, 'Wait, there's one more thing we have to put in there'.
This Christmas tree decoration
is brushing your teeth.  This is the last little detail
that means you are putting your Buddhahood.  These are the little things that make a Buddha.
This is not a big deal.  It's not a big deal.  It is attention
to the small details of
making others happy that creates buddhas.
Next.
See if you remember this one.  I'll give you a hint - yamantaka, yamantaka.
This is the famous lamrim story.
Monks and nuns must attend sojong twice a month and confess their
wrongdoings to each other
openly.
The teacher said,
...they hit gunty.  They hit a gunty
which is a special piece of wood, looks like a 2x4
and you hit it with another stick and it goes thunk, thunk, thunk...
and it was an old fashioned bell before metal became common.
They would hit the board, and when you heard it
you had to go to the sojong.  They still do it.
I made gunty with my teacher.  He wanted one
and we made it to the exact dimensions.
There are all these rules about it.
When you hear gunty
you should.... you hold it here..
you hold the gunty here and you hit it like this.
Then all the monks and nuns should come to confession.
This teacher said, 'hey, they hit gunty.  Come on.'
The students said, 'No, I will not confess today.'
The teacher said, 'What?'
It is one of the main commitments of a monk, to go to sojong.
The teacher said, 'What are you talking about?'  He said, 'I don't need to go today.'
The teacher said, 'What do you mean you don't have to go today?'
He said, 'Did you forget, you gave me a yamantaka initiation yesterday?
I am yamantaka, I am Buddha.  I don't need to go to Sojong anymore.'  The
teacher pulled his ears, saying, 'What is this, you yamantika?
Yamantika will go to sojong with me now.'
What it means is, don't give me the excuse that you are a great tantrika,
and you are above morality and
now you have a higher vision -
that is a completely wrong idea!
If you have a secret initiation
then you have to go to sojong every morning or something.
You have to go further than anyone else.
Because that's what gives you...
gives power to your tantra practice.  Treat others well
and admit when you make a mistake.
Next.
This is a sad picture.  We always think of morality as the root
of our practice, the basis of our practice.
Pabongka Rinpoche, kind of flipped it around.
This is a perfect picture.
He said, imagine an apple tree
that has been cut in half.  Actually, he used a palm tree.
Someone sliced ​​and cut the top of the tree.
So you won't get any leaves, not
even a single leaf will come out.
Therefore, you will not earn interest.
Therefore, you will not get the fruits that always come from the flowers.
You will get nothing.
A person who is unkind to others day after day, hour after hour,
they cut off every opportunity
to gain the beautiful fruits of practice.
Next.
This is an idea from something my teacher asked me...
Sorry, I asked my teacher and I don't know if you remember but I asked him.
The first of the five paths, the path of accumulation,
you attain it when you have personal tragedy,
but if you are on the bodhisattva path,
you attain it when you gain bodhichitta.
I said, I don't understand what's tragic about bodhichitta?
And he said, 'No, no, no.
This is still a tragedy theme.
The tragedy of every living creature, every creature in the entire universe is
experiencing the same tragedy.'
Communal tragedy is the beginning of five paths.
Thinking about the tragedy
is the beginning of the five paths for a bodhisattva.
So yes, it is the same.  The
puppy was having a hard time, but now all the puppies in the basket were having a hard time.
We are all in this together.
And that is the beginning of bodhichitta.
Next image.
This is a man shaking hands with someone in their office.
I imagined the woman introducing them.  This is Joe, he works in the advertising department.
and this is Sam, he works in the computer department.
They shook hands.  Do
you remember what this is?
It was a very, very funny exercise where we were supposed to close our eyes
and think of the person who annoys us the most.
And see if we can feel the anger.  The problem with exercises like this
is that after about 10 minutes you forget it's an exercise.
You're really getting angry!
Let me see if I can make myself angry.
How would you do it?
I'm going to think about this person who gave me a hard time this week.  'Okay, go ahead'.
Then slowly the person started to tremble.  You ask, 'What happened?'
I'm angry. The experiment worked.
If it were your 'old', they would say,
'check what it felt like the first time you thought about this person.'
How does it feel? What arises in your heart?
I don't know about you, but I experience a little bit of irritation in my heart.
I start to feel a kind of discomfort here or there.
When I think about someone who has bothered me or a problem that has bothered me,
I can intentionally generate tension
within myself.
He said, 'Let's practice—try to trigger some tension in your heart,
then notice that tension and recognize it, as if you were shaking hands with someone.
Recognize what it feels like
when mental suffering, negative emotions
first arise in your heart and keep practicing.
As soon as you feel better, and you forget about this person,
then think about them again.
See if you can get angry again.
See if you can start getting angry again.
Try to become familiar with what it feels like, shaking hands. 'Hi. This is Geshe Michael.
Hi. What's your name?
I'm starting to get upset with this person.
Nice to meet you. Now I know what you look like.
Now I can be careful. I can avoid you in the future.'
Next.
This is called visiting the middle of the sun.
This lamrim theme, which is Love in the Time of Viruses.
Viruses are a big thing,  and it's spreading all over the world.
I've lived a long time and I thought I'd seen it all.
I was entering my 60s and thought by now nothing new was going to happen.
I was pretty much prepared for anything.
I'd seen it all and nothing could upset me too much. Then this virus came along and threatened everyone in the world.
Wow, that's a big deal, it's covering the entire planet.
I don't know if it's happened to you, but it's happened to me.
This is probably the ninth vice, which is envy; being
happy when other people have problems.
When I hear that famous, annoying people are sick.
I don't want them to die or anything, but
... I say it's bad to be bad.
And then I catch myself thinking like that.
It feels like a big deal.
It feels like this problem has spread all over the planet.
It feels like it's something that's hard for me to deal with.
We've just entered,
after 10 years of studying the lamrim,
and we've actually been pointing the way for people with greater capacity.
We're going to open that study
with the idea of ​​bodhichitta. What is bodhichitta?
It's not the enlightenment of the mind. Forget the bad translation, the translation is very good.  Bad.
It's my hope that I can become a buddha to help countless sentient beings.
There's that direct experience, just as
there's the direct experience of emptiness.
There's a parallel experience that
we have to aim for in this life, and again, you have to be in meditation.
We're describing an extraordinary... what you might call... breakthrough...
threshold experience
when you enter a deep state of meditation.
Because space and time come from seeds,
if you can play with these seeds,
then you can package space and time.
In a meditation that takes no more than half an hour,
you can literally visit
every person in the universe,
including animals, insects, birds, and fish.
You can communicate with each individual
in that half hour.
You can make a commitment to each one.
You meet them, you see each person suffering,
each one having a difficult life and worrying about the future.
You can go to each one individually and say,
"I'll take care of it, don't worry."
I used to work when I was in university.
I got a scholarship, but they said you had to work a certain number of hours a week.
It turned out to be 30 hours a week.
I had to drive a truck.
Actually, at first they put me in  In the cafeteria, they said you'll be mopping the cafeteria floor.
I quit after 10 hours. I quit the first day.
Then they said, "You can drive a truck." I said, "That's fun. I'll drive a truck."
I drove a truck for five years.
There was a guy, a
full-time employee of the university named Big John.
His name was Big John. He was Polish, seven feet tall, a big guy.
Everyone was scared when they saw him.
They were afraid of him, but he was very sweet.
He brought donuts to work, and he was from Trenton, New Jersey.
He would do the best things for us and he would take care of us. One day we wrecked a truck.
We hit a tree with the truck and we wrecked it.
He took care of us, saying, "Oh, this screw wasn't tight enough.
I don't know what happened. The truck is wrecked. Don't blame these guys.
Don't blame this young man.
They just drove it."
Then he winked at us and said, "I've done you a favor."  I've helped you guys."
I always think of him when I think of bodhichitta.
You'll meet every living being in the universe face to face.
And you'll say, "Big John has taken care of you.  I take care of you.  Don't worry.
Don't think about it. I'm taking care of you.
That's bodhichitta. You have to have that experience.
You have to attain that experience. You have to meditate.
You have to study bodhichitta.
You have to study the lamrim of bodhichitta.
You have to do all the steps;
exchanging self and others...
One day you will have that experience and you will meet every living being.
You will say to them, 'I'm taking care of you.' Don't worry. I'm helping you.'
Big Mike is taking care of you, or Big Tim, or Big Seiji.
Don't worry.
Don't stress. I'm on top of it! That's what it feels like
. It's a personal commitment.
Why are we talking about it?
You'll do it in countless worlds. When you do it, the day you do it,
you'll do it in countless worlds.
An act done directly with every living being in countless worlds,
no problem taking care of a single virus in a single world.
It's nothing. A
virus that harms
7 or 8 billion people is nothing compared to bodhichitta.
We say, if you spill ketchup on your shirt
and take it to the middle of a 25 million-degree sun,
maybe the ketchup stain will come off.
You probably don't have to worry about the ketchup stain. Work on your bodhichitta.
You'll destroy the virus, accidentally. It's
no big deal.
Next picture.
Don't mess around with other paths.
Learn bodhichitta. Learn to have this experience.
Don't waste your time.
Don't focus on anything else. Focus on bodhichitta.
Then you won't have to do anything twice.
We're talking about doing everything.  Twice. This woman was in a hurry.
She said, I don't have time for this bodhichitta stuff.
I'm going straight to tantra.
You're still going to have to go back and get the thing you forgot,
which is bodhichitta.
Work on your bodhichitta first.
You don't have to go back and get bodhichitta and go all the way.
This is a radical example in the next picture.
It's hard to remember. I'll give you some time to think about it.
I don't know if you remember this.
It's a bit complicated.
A group of 60 men and women were about to attain nirvana just by seeing emptiness directly, and
without bodhichitta, nirvana is lower.
Manjushri appeared and taught them about bodhichitta.
Maybe he was teaching them about the experience we just talked about.
They were all upset with Manjushri. They were like, don't waste our time.
We're close to nirvana. We can feel it. We can feel it.
We've all seen emptiness, don't waste our time.
Don't talk to us about this.
Because they didn't respect the teachings about bodhichitta,
they went to hell.
They didn't go to heaven. They went to the realm of  hell.
And they burned
and they became humans again after millions of years.
Deep inside were the bodhichitta teachings that Manjushri gave them and they remembered them.
They become Bodhisattvas and they become Buddhas.
It will take a shorter time, than
going to lower nirvana without learning bodhichitta.
It would be quicker to go to hell
and come back
and start again with bodhichitta,
then if you don't use bodhichitta
and you go to lower nirvana.
This is a picture of someone misleading someone else on purpose.
This woman asked;
Which is the highway to the shop I want to visit?
The man knew the highway was closed.
He told him, 'Don't go through there because the highway is closed.  Go another way.
And he insisted, 'No,
tell me where the highway I want is.'
Then he lied to her,
saying, 'Take this path that's actually further, the one the man wants the woman to take.'
This is a story about skillful means.
Next picture.
This is a warm-up before you enter a race.
Usually, what do we use this picture for? Do you remember?
It's breath meditation.
Usually, we say breath meditation is a warm-up. Don't think of it as a race.
In the Olympics, there's no contest for stretching before a race. There's
no such thing; you don't get a gold medal for stretching.
In this case, we're not talking about breath meditation. We're talking about, it's
better to do the three main paths in sequence.
Feeling sad about this world.
Striving to have a direct experience of bodhichitta.
Seeing emptiness so you can help everyone.
Warming up by feeling sad about this life first.
Next picture.
We're almost done. I think we're very close. Are we close? Not that close. Okay.
Do you remember who these guys are? They're a really bad band.
I guess you met them at a shopping mall or something, singing bad songs.
They're called, 'the opening act.'
Step on the path to a lower capacity;
try to  Getting a higher rebirth.
Stepping on the path to medium capacity,
trying not to return to this world at all.
Stepping on the path to greater capacity.
These two levels are just the opening acts.
This is the main thing, leading to bodhichitta. What's above bodhichitta?
There are six perfections. Check them out:
steps on the path to keeping your ass
out of the lower hells, steps on the path to getting to nirvana,
and then we have bodhichitta.
This is the experience of meeting every sentient being
and making a commitment that I will take care of you.
Up here is the sixth.
That's six in Chinese.
Up here are the six perfections.
Now, which one is the big deal? Which one is the
real band? Which one is the opening act?
These people are clear, lower nirvana is no big deal.
What's interesting is, Pabongka Rinpoche said,
that experience
with every sentient being
is the main act.
That's the focus I want you to have.
I want you to try to have that experience.
If you have that experience, we can talk about the six perfections,
including number six, which is seeing emptiness.
We'll talk about that later.
Come on, I want you to focus on this experience.
By the way, a good way  To have that experience is to imagine the experience and try to listen to the description.
Pretend you can do it and keep pretending.
Keep doing it.
It feels like a slot machine.
I want to say, it feels like a slot machine.
When you push the button on a slot machine,
these pictures spin;
cherries, and other pictures.
Not that I've ever played a slot machine. Well, once, with my dad.
You push the stick and then the numbers move like this.
Just imagine
your mom's face coming up.
You say, 'Your mom looks worried.' She's like, 'Yeah, I'm worried about life.'
You say, 'Don't worry, Big John's got you covered.'
Relax. I understand. I'm on top of it.
Then a picture of your father appears.
Not just the picture, but the person appears.
It feels like that in meditation. Try to imagine it. Try to practice.
It will trigger the real thing.
It will trigger the real thing. Bring people in, one by one.
See how they feel.
Make a commitment. Don't worry. I'm taking care of you. I'm on top of it.
Then they pass. Bring someone else in.
Practice like that. You can do five or six people.
It will get faster, because times will change.
Pabongka Rinpoche said that was the main act.
It was the Rolling Stones.
The others were just new bands that weren't very good.
Who was the last one? Did they have a final act? Usually not.
Anyway, the rest just left the stadium or something. Never mind.
Now we're moving on to the
10 cool things about gaining bodhichitta.
We'll only have time to do the first one in this lamrim. The
first cool thing about gaining bodhichitta is...
if you were a nerd
who played tennis in school.
Your dream was to be on the team.
Next picture.
Yes, there's Geshe Michael in the middle.
At the top, isn't it?  The strange people below.
You can join the team. It's great to be on the Bodhisattva team.
Work to be on that team. It's
really cool to be on that team,
because it spans the universe.
It's all these cool people all over the universe. It's really cool to be part of that team.
It's sweet.
That's the first benefit of bodhichitta.
Next picture:
This is a man visiting an art museum.
He talks about two levels of tantra: the first level is meeting angels, and the
second level is studying how to become angels and become angels.
In the first level,
we're supposed to actually meet
real angels in person.
It's not like standing in an art museum and looking at a statue or a thangka of someone.
This is meeting them in person, and that's a completely different thing.
If you try to practice tantra
without the experience of bodhichitta, it's like looking at a picture of Buddha
instead of meeting Buddha.
They don't like talking to people who don't have bodhichitta.
They feel more comfortable
around people who have this experience. Try to have this experience.
Then tantra will work for you.
If you don't have this experience,
tantra will be difficult.
It's like looking at pictures of Buddhas instead of meeting them.  They.
Next.
If you try to practice tantra without bodhichitta, you might get bad results.
We're talking about the first nuclear tests
in modern times.
Scientists acknowledged that this explosion
might ignite the entire world.
They were just trying to do something cool.
But they were gambling with a major disaster.
That's tantra without bodhichitta.
It's like accidentally setting the sky on fire. You're going to mess it up.
Next.
Even small, neutral karma
becomes powerful for someone with bodhichitta.
Someone with bodhichitta can feed the birds,
make a prayer about it,
and influence millions of people. They have this power.
Next picture.
Even a small bad deed like stealing French fries to feed the birds can become powerful if done by a bodhisattva.
But this is a dangerous practice. We're not at that level. We're not at that level. We're not at that level.
You hear that? No?
We have a picture of
fugu fish.
People in Japan, like macho men, eat this fish.
There are very, very poisonous parts that can kill you instantly. 50 people a year die in Japan.
But people still go to restaurants. They serve this fish.  In a restaurant,
you need three years of special training or you'll kill someone.
It's like stealing French fries to give them to a bird
because you want to help the bird.
We're not at that level. Don't eat fugu if you're not trained.
Then we have this great picture of Nick and Erin
with their big boss,
Amalie.
Amalie represents the Buddha,
and Nick
represents the father,
which is bodhichitta, and Erin represents wisdom,
which is the direct perception of emptiness.
In some way,
somehow, I don't know what this belief is in Asia, but in some way the father is irreplaceable. There's
something special about the father.
I don't know what it is. But anyway...
You can see emptiness at different levels,
on all three tracks.
But bodhichitta, you have to be special.
You can only see it on the highest track.
Define yourself
as someone on the higher track.
You need both to have a baby who is Buddhahood.
Next picture.
We said thuk dam gyi thil. The
Yang Team correctly identified today.
What is your main practice? What is the number one thing in your life right now?
Until the next lamrim, Medicine Buddha lamrim.  ..
...I want you to treat this as your main practice.
Try to have the experience of meeting countless beings.
Try to have that experience.
I don't care if you sit there for hours and nothing happens,
just try, just pretend.
Get into your mind until the next lamrim.
Let's make a deal like that. Make it your main practice.
Next picture.
If the practice wasn't so important then one of the greatest Buddhists of all time, Lord Atisha, wouldn't have sailed for
13 months risking his life to get the teachings on
bodhichitta that you just got
in this video. And you don't have to go anywhere.
If Atisha thought it was worth risking his life for 13 months
on a small boat
in the Pacific Ocean and the Indian Ocean, then maybe
it's important, maybe it's worth it.
Next picture.
I think the stupidest thing you can do in your entire life is to go to Paris and not buy a croissant.
Okay. I'm just saying, there are probably other stupid things you can do in life.
But to me the stupidest thing
is to go to Paris and not go to a bakery? At least
buy one.  A crepe
on the street
with... what chocolate is that?
Nutella, yes.
There is no Nutella crepe.
To go to Paris and not eat a Nutella crepe is to prove you're crazy.
If you study the lamrim,
if you've gotten this far in the lamrim, and Geshela has been teaching for 10 years,
you eventually get to the croissant,
which is the bodhisattva experience.
Don't be crazy and leave Paris without eating one. Don't leave the lamrim without having this experience.
You're an idiot.
We're done with the croissant. I thought you wanted to make a presentation?
No, I guess there might be a croissant in that bag?
Tim Lowenhaupt
is going to make a formal presentation
for Geshela, my pay.
Oh, that's a pande? What do you call it?
What's it called? This
chocolate pande here. You have to divide it into three pieces.
And give me all three, I mean no, just one.
I have a chocolate pande.
This is what you give your teachers when they teach you about bodhichitta.
Let's make a deal.
For the next few months
work on that experience. Do the chapters.  Dedicate yourself to your Shantideva meditation.
Try to work towards having that experience. The worst that can happen, at least
you'll have planted the seed in your mind for having this experience.
Just pretend.
Just sit and fantasize about it. Fantasizing is a great meditation.
Fantasize that you're having this experience of meeting,
one by one,
every sentient being.
You're making a personal commitment with each one
to take care of them in the best way possible.
Okay. See you at the next lamrim for Medicine Buddha. Yay!